He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to
fall, and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts
are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they
will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc. Chapter 48 verses 4-5. The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is
He's nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints in our...
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, giant killers,
dragon slayers, as fixators of sphinxes,
youth listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast,
and this is episode 118.
I have spent hundreds of hours of my life
talking to you on this podcast, Father Stephen Dion.
What do you have to say for yourself?
I think the benefits I've given to your life,
even even be a
well beyond those those granted to any listeners anything they might have
derived is incalculable and you're welcome. Okay so my co-host Father Stephen
Dionne the end to ran off the Antwives is with me straight from the swamp and
Lafayette Louisiana. I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas Pennsylvania
purchased precariously atop the Arcane Tower of Podcasting, hovering dozens dozens
of stories above a disused gateway to the underworld.
is only slightly a joke, by the way, everybody.
I've had people ask me, they're like,
are you wait, what do you mean?
Is that a joke?
And beneath me, there once was a crematorium.
This building was an actual funeral home
where they incinerated human bodies down in the basement.
So, I mean, that is pretty much a gateway
to the underworld.
And we are alive, unlike those people.
If you are listening to us live,
you can call us a some of them.
Some of them.
They'd be a lot of seeking.
Yes.
Yes, experiencing the first president, God willing.
I hope.
I hope you can call.
Come on, man, let me get through the pattern at the beginning.
You can call city five, five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six, just like the voice
of Steve just said and talk to us.
And we'll get to your calls beginning the second half.
And Mike, raisin brand again will be taking those calls.
brand being the greatest of all wedding gifts.
Really? You can have to break that up for me.
You don't know that story?
No. No. Tell us the story, Uncle Steve.
Okay. Well, this is a...
I'm just intrigued now.
Oh yeah. No. My last encounter with Father John Bear
was just him ridiculing me about this.
Huh. Like in person. The last time I was with him in person.
Like, was just him attacking me over this...
This grim reality that I'm about to reveal.
So I'm getting...
married to my wife, right? So this is like 17 years ago now. And she felt as some brides to be
feel that perhaps her groom to be, is that participating fully or enough in the wedding planning process?
In my defense, there were many areas in which my participation was not entirely welcomed.
I feel like I know that.
story. Yes. So what task which was given to me was to help participate in the construction
of our bridal registries, right? Like the the store registries. Yeah, of course, of course.
And a little scanning gun. Yes, my my then fiance sent to me, you can select either to
but together the registry.
for Craten barrel or target. Now I had never been to a Craten barrel. I mean,
you need any crates or barrels as far as I get.
Guy. Therefore I said, uh, target, I have been there before. And it's cheaper. So that should appeal to your
does the first time because they had very affordable prices. The one in San Bernardino, California, at
least on masters of the universe figures when I was a child. But
So that's a target.
So target, hopefully, when you're putting the other
bridal registry, they would log into it and then they would hand you a scanning gun.
Yeah.
So you could just walk through the store and by scanning things, put them on the registry,
right?
So I thoughtfully went through the store, put some things on there I thought we might
need.
I tried to put a range of gifts, right, for various price ranges, right?
You
So it would not be untoward, but you know, I have Dutch uncles, right?
And so while doing this, and as I'm going through the target, I thought to myself, self, I said,
I enjoy myself a bowl of raisin brand in the morning.
I eat it in a very weird way, but that's another story for another time.
So I scanned a box of raisin brand.
by putting a box of raisin brand on our wedding ring.
at the time my then fiance was still living in California. And so she went to check to see if I had
performed this task which she had assigned me and discovered the raised brand on the wedding registry.
She found this absurd. She was working at the time as a nurse. She said to the doctor, she was working
with that day. My fiance I send
to target to put together a wedding registry and he puts this box of raisin brand on there.
The doctor looked at her and said, did he also put milk?
She said no. And the doctor said, well that's ridiculous then. You can't eat raisin brand without milk.
So she then just spent I think some time puzzling over the nature of the male members of the species
human. I mean she didn't know you.
well at that point. And their thought patterns. Yeah. Oh, that's not true. I'm a complicated
man. And no one understands me but my woman. But my woman does understand me. Yeah. So
father John bearer around the time we're actually getting married found out about this.
And seem to take some kind of weird personal affront. Huh? To the fact that I had put
raise and brand on my wedding registry.
Like
He was upset like it was as if I had to file something holy and I'm like, I don't think
father that a target wedding registry is sacrosanct, right?
This way that I should be berated for having solid it with raisin bread, which is after
all affordifying and healthy food.
And good for you in multiple ways.
Multiple ways.
Yeah.
Right?
raise the bread as the closest I come to eating fruit.
uh poor vegetables but uh you see you report milk all over it i'm Dutch got it the dairy um
yeah so he was very incensed about it but the the real day pneumo of this story is that
on our wedding day the time came at the reception
in Newcastle, Pennsylvania of all places to open our wedding gifts
And lo and behold one of my uncles had bought me a box of
raisin bread and then stuff some cash inside it.
Because it's breakfast ever.
If no one else, my uncle Jim has always understood my ways.
So yes, that is that is the I put raisin bread on my wedding registry.
Wow.
And we didn't even have to do like a fundraiser to get that snow.
Everybody got that once for free kids.
First one's for A, then I...
I get you. I did have someone the other night even though I haven't finished the intro here yet, but I did have
Someone the other night live asked me in person they're like tell us the whole thing about James old Jones and father Steven. I was like look I can't that's but I did tell them that you do have a justified grievance.
Yes against that man and not only made worse by the fact that my years log play to dance on his grave was completely foiled when he was cremated.
right. He got the leave it in death.
He tasks me.
Okay.
All right.
Tonight onto our actual topic for the night, which is yeah, I mean, or I'm into
that. I think we just pivot to brazen brand and James old Jones, but maybe we should also
talk about Moses.
I was trying to introduce orcas with salmon hats, but orcas was salmon hats at the
other.
The real story from you.
There's not every one's mind that we've thus far ignored.
You kids there in the YouTube chats.
Did you guys know that sometimes kill
whales more properly known as orcas. Sometimes we're dead salmon hats. It's an
actual thing. There's going to be somebody that started up again recently. Yeah, it's
a weird fashion, just like mullets and moustaches are back. So are orca dead salmon hats.
Yeah. We are talking about Moses and specifically the majority of Moses. That was another
beautiful segue right there wasn't it but we are talking about
Moses. It was not an orca.
Nor did he ever wear a sabbatat just for you. Yes.
So how does the authority of Moses work exactly? Does he have authority over killer whales?
What was the relationship of his authority to other leaders in Israel who governed the
salmon and what happened to that authority when he died?
So I thought I would start us off by asking this question, why isn't.
the leadership authority of Israel, like the way that they were organized.
Why isn't that something that most American Christians have probably heard in these
like sermons about or Sunday school lessons about?
Like why is this just kind of off the radar?
Even though it's, I mean as we're going to see, it's very clearly spelled out in the
old testament.
Yes.
Well, I mean this goes back to something we talked about in our episodes on the Torah, where
when we talked about this
official division that was made not only by Calvin but famously by Calvin.
Yeah.
Between these, you know, sort of, and it's an ad hoc distinction between these elements
of quote, quote, the law where there is a, there are, there's civil law, ceremonial
law, and moral law.
Right.
And then civil and ceremonial are said to be sort of done away with now that Christ is here
or fulfilled not abolished but you know,
does bend either way. And then the moral law, right, well that that continues to be an effect.
Right. Now there's all kinds of problems with this that we talked about back then, right?
One of the big ones is that it's an ad hoc distinction, right? In the sense that like
the tour
itself does not make such a distinction. And so you get a lot of arguments then about, well,
is this moral, meaning it's still an effect, or is this ceremonial or civil, right? Exhibit A of
this, completely non-controversial example, one of the ways in which people who are
are more pro the acceptance of homosexual act.
activity within the church make is the way they try to get around sort of the clear
condemnations of the Old Testament as they try to argue, well, this isn't talking about
gay people.
This is talking about cult prostitutes.
So this is part of the ceremonial law.
Therefore, don't worry about it anymore.
Wow.
This is very common.
This is very common argument.
Yeah.
Very common argument, right?
You better have long arms to make a reach like that.
that whole thing.
is facilitated by the idea that there is this division,
which is again completely ad hoc.
And this is a place where,
so there was a fellow who was somewhat critical
of our recent episodes critiquing dispensationalism.
And especially when we said that on certain things,
there was a certain amount of cope going on among dispensationalists.
Right. And his rejoinder was always, it's not coped. They have an answer. They make this distinction.
Okay. Making these ad hoc distinctions is coped. It is definitionally coped.
Right. So when you show a Calvinist, right? See, this person was also very happy when we were
picking on Calvinist. He just got upset when we were talking about dispensationalists.
These by the way are some of my favorite
comments on Lord of Spirits are the father steve it is normally right on until he criticized
something I believe and now he's totally off base that doesn't know what he's talking about.
Isn't that true?
When he criticized everyone else he's so sharp why is it he doesn't understand what I believe?
Well the only reason why he would ever listen to a podcast or read a book is to have what you
already believed confirmed.
Exactly!
It's to figure out...
That's if they agree with what you already think.
Yeah.
But so when you show a Calvinist, right, God wills that none should perish.
And he says, well, that's talking, that's not talking about his permissive will.
That's how a Decreative will.
These are two different things.
That's cope.
Yeah.
That's making a distinction that's not the text to get around with the text clearly.
I mean, with Calvinist, you can always tell because they use this phrase in such a way
as yeah, right.
That's making these distinctions.
Right? Yes.
God creates everything and foreridates everything that happens, but in such a way that he's not the author of evil.
That's cope. These distinctions are cope. Lots of people do them on lots of things. Okay.
If they're not germane to, if they're not proper to the text you're referring to, and what you're interpreting, if they're ad hoc, in other words, they are cope.
And so the same thing is traditionalism.
One of the examples for one of his comments was when we were talking about...
about Joshua saying that all of the land promises have been fulfilled.
Just crystal clear clear is that, right?
It's like, well, they distinguish between, they were fulfilled according to type,
but not according to extent.
Wow.
This is an ad hoc distinction made nowhere in the text.
But on top of that, I understand how typology works.
Right.
In fact, in that episode, we appealed to typology.
The left
was a type of the kingdom of heaven. They want to have the land be a type of more land
in the future. There's a big any sense. That's all. That's all cope. But so is this distinction
between, right? Because it's part of trying to argue your way around.
fact that Christ says the law is not abolished. Right? But there's still parts of it that you
want to say don't apply anymore. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, and you can always talk
distinctions. And you can always tell when someone's pulling this or the much, I would say,
the much less learned for lack of a better word way of doing is when people say, oh, well,
That was the old testament.
You know, and they just sort of wave their hands at most of wave their hands away at most of the Bible.
You know, yes. Well, yeah, that's this cognitive dissonance of is this not the Bible? Is this not scripture?
Right? You can't bow well, you can. That's why it's cognitive dissonance. Hold in your mind the idea that every word of it is still scripture, but on the other hand, chunks of it are completely irrelevant.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's that's a rough cognitive
Dissidents to hold to yeah, right and so but that that I think honestly is why no one
Addresses this but that means essentially all the passages dealing with this
Become meaningless
Yeah, and therefore kind of unfamiliar to people yeah, they're just weird historical data
Oh, yeah, that's a thing that happened it actually is real right yeah, that's how they did it then
Yeah, but it's got no on
going relevance as scripture to how the church is formed, how the Christian life is formed,
or anything remotely similar. That's a problem. Well, let's deproblematize it. Yes. So,
we're, yes, and that's what, that's the problem we are here to address in this and the next
episode. And part of this just to give a give us a rare shout out. Part of what we're going to be
Deely with the night is inspired by a project I've been working on with my friend
Doc Branson. Oh, I will speak not more of this but all right just a big teaser
there's cryptic throw that out there. There are things of foot at the circle K.
Right, so if we believe as Christians ought that scriptures
including the Christian Old Testament are still relevant and are still scriptures. And some of the
scriptures we're going to be talking about the passages. They're going to be talking about in detail
tonight are read in the Orthodox Church like at Vespers, at Feasts. Yeah. That's right. So this is not
just like Father Stephen has decided this is still relevant because he's anti-Semitic and a
and the Judy eyes are at the same time.
This is, you know, the church proclaims its relevance quite regularly.
But so if we operate that this is still relevant, okay,
how, what kind of authority did Moses have an exercise in his life in Israel?
And what happened to it after Moses?
Then...
because you could also take the position, which is sort of the position that the people who divvy up the law that way, the Torah that way, take that, okay, whatever, right?
That's how it worked for Moses, but Moses dead. Right? Right? So it's not super relevant. But as we will see this evening, it didn't just go away with Moses.
Um, no, we're talking about Moses.
As we did in the episodes talking about the history of Israel, I like to start by sort
of reframing the life of Moses.
Because we need to get an idea of, right, Moses as a person.
Because a lot of the understanding of what authority he had and how he exercised it requires
Here's us to see him as a person who's living.
a life and doing things in the real world with other real people, right? How he interacted
with the Israelites, right? What kind of a thought? Because he's actually, this isn't just
a theoretical authority and a systematic theology book, you know, in a footnote on Old Testament
ordination or something. This is, right, something that actually took place, right? And it has
on going continued relevance. So Moses...
our best sources say lived 120 years. And that means his life, and this is brought out in the Torah itself, his life can be neatly divided into three, forty years sort of chapters.
Almost like an episode of Lord of Spirits.
I mean, each of these chapters does feel like it takes 40 years sometimes.
I'll tell you what.
What is preparatory to the one that comes next because as we've talked about in the show the number 40 we're talking about 40 days 40 years
40 is this sort of preparatory number
I mean to do with 42 being six sevens which causes you then to expect the seventh seven
And so the first 40 years of Moses life is
Spent as a member of Pharaoh's court minus maybe the first couple of months. Yeah, he's growing up as an option horn
But again, keep this in mind.
At the time he leaves and goes to the desert of Midian, he's 40 already.
So he is not just an adult, he's fully an adult.
He's a mature adult.
So there's a whole life he lives in Egypt.
And a whole education he receives there and all of that and all of that is then
preparatory to the next chapter. The next chapter is he's in Midian. He meets his wife
Zappora, works for his father-in-law, Jethro, overseeing his herds and sheep. They're in the wilderness,
has kids. He does that.
for another 40 years. Yeah, so he's 80 by the time right most of the what we think of his life
of Moses happens. Yes, so 40 to 80 is this whole life with as part of an extended family
with his own family subunit within that right lives a whole second life right also for 40 years
Which means that
preparatory to the next thing. That's preparatory to him meeting God. So he spends
40 years learning all the ways of the world, right, in the greatest, arguably the
greatest superpower in the world at the time. I think I'm going to date on a
good argument about the date of the Exodus. Then spends another lifetime living as a
Nomad with.
other descendants of Abraham
Living basically the way Abraham lived and Isaac and Jacob a
Whole life then when he's 80 he meets God at Mount Sinai or at meets God
On the Mount in the burning bush and so all the things we think of
Well, we think of stuff Moses did
Right like we asked somebody hey list the stuff Moses did
Right?
They might mention growing up in Pharaoh's household briefly.
Yeah
Right
They're probably not gonna talk about the 40 years of living as a nomadic shepherd or a nomadic herdsman
Right, it raising a family. They're gonna skip to all the exciting stuff that happens in the last 40 years from 80 to 120
This third life he lives
where
You know, everything happens.
You can front's Pharaoh calls down the plagues,
call it a gig of the Passover,
the Cross of the Red Sea,
during the Mount Sinai,
receiving the Torah Mount Sinai,
moving off from all of the issues
with the Israelites he deals with.
Everything out, that's this last 40 years,
this last period, right?
And that's preparing him for the kingdom of heaven.
That's why that's 40 years.
And so it is, but even during that last 40 years, right, all of those things we think of,
all those things we list, all the stuff we remember Charlton Heston doing, or I guess is
Prince of Egypt still a live thing for like Zoomers and Gen Alpha?
Or is there some Moses mobile game or something?
I don't know.
Someone did in the chat mention Prince of Egypt hoping we were going to give a sorry Prince
of Egypt.
Oh, moments. I have to say I kind of liked the Prince of Egypt soundtrack. I thought it was
had some moments. I don't remember the soundtrack really at all. Other than other than them singing
after seeing the song of the scene. That's the only song I actually remember from it. But
yeah, there was a sequel about Joseph. There was. I didn't know that. Joseph, like King of Dreams
or Prince of Dreams, something like that. Oh, with Ben Affleck voicing Joseph. Oh yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. He's the only person to play Superman, Batman, and Joseph from the book of Genesis.
I.
Unless. Yeah. No, that's print. No, there's no chance.
It's like there's half a chance Michael Keaton maybe was in a production of Joseph in the
Technicolor Dreamcoat, but my favorite Superman.
My favorite crossover of that kind is that Kiana Reeves played Hamlet up in Canada somewhere.
And you know, would have walked in on Rosencranston-Gilderner and Sternin said,
my excellent friends.
So that was a cosmotype casting.
Right? Exactly.
Yes.
And the question is whether that right will make it into the editing that Mike is going to do after this,
because now this is a big debate.
Exactly how to edit the Lord of Spirits podcast, but we'll never announce.
He might just edit out me saying this.
He could. All my best jokes, killing room.
floor. I know. I think people assume that. I'll let them go out assuming it. But so even
in those last 40 years, if you take all those things from those movies or wherever else,
on the tweet talks or whatever the kids are into these days, they're watching about Moses.
All those things we think about, those big things, take place in, if you put them all together,
I mean, they didn't all happen together.
But take place in...
over the course of several weeks. There's not really 40 years worth of stuff there.
So most of that 40 years, even that last 40 years, Moses was doing what?
He was dealing with his wives and his children and his extended family
and his herds. He was dealing with all the things of daily life in a big bedoing camp at the
the middle of the
desert. Yeah, just live in life, right? Collecting mana as we
mean, he's he's the head of a tribe. He's the head of the tribe of
Levi, right? Right. So he's not just like it's not like, oh, he's
the king or whatever of Israel or he's the cult leader, right, he's
part of a tribe. He's part of a clan within that tribe among the
Levi's, right? And he's got all those duties and responsibilities.
That's most of his life. And so we talk about him exercising
authority.
We're primarily not talking about those big things.
We're not, when we say the authority given to Moses,
we're not talking about like the ability to work signs and wonders.
Okay.
Because guess what?
You don't have that.
Right.
He's there is no one listening to this who has that.
Because if you had that, you wouldn't be listening to us.
God can have other things he would have you doing.
Not listening to this.
Yeah. You've got doing signs and wonders.
Yeah.
You don't be like, wow.
Father Stevens raised in Brand-Anacodus hysterical.
hysterical
right, you would be out prophesying, okay?
That's, or you would be deep in prayer somewhere.
You would not have time for this shakhanary.
So, but that's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about the authority he exercised day to day
in his life, interacting with the people of Israel,
interacting with the members of his extended family,
interacting with the members of his clan
and of his tribe and of the Israelites in general,
day-to-day.
Moses is the guy with some kind of, and that's what we're going to work through here, authority.
Right. And that means something in the sense that he was exercising it. He was using it. He was
doing it. It wasn't just a theoretical thing. It wasn't just like, oh, we've all got a picture
of Moses in our tent, and we sing a song to dear leader every morning. Right. That's not
did either right we know quite the
They did not admire and look up to Moses.
That bug me is realized.
I think I'm threatening to kill him and go back to Egypt and stuff.
But it's about how he actually exercised authority.
And the place where we tend to kind of think about this, right, is in the context of,
well, he was like a judge, right.
And we tend to think of that not in the sense of the judges and the book of judges.
but in the sense of like he was hearing cases and sort of like court cases.
Latin has done this to you people. Latin be very deep in your in your culture has
caused you to think about everything as a dang court case man. It's made
lawyers of us all. That's not really most of what he was doing, right? So I'm sure
there was a little bit.
Right. This guy stole my goat. No, I didn't. Right.
But most of what we mean in terms of him judging cases was more akin to him answering questions,
more akin to him to making what we would call judgment calls. Yeah. Right. Like, what is the right
thing to do to this in the situation? How does this commandment apply to this situation? Right.
There's this weird situation that arises
in real life that there isn't a commandment that literally indirectly addresses.
Right? You could argue from this one commandment that you should do X. You could argue from this
other one that you should do Y. What should I do? Right? This is most of what Moses is doing.
This is most of what Moses is doing. It's like being a parent, you know, especially once
your kids get to a certain age, there's a whole lot of adjudication that goes on.
Yes, so...
This is most of what he's doing and
And if you're a parish priest you do a lot of this as well
Yeah, yeah
But if you want a perfect example of how this works in scripture
Good news we've got one for you
And that is in Exodus chapter 13
Yep, okay, so starting with the verse one
The Lord said to Moses,
to me all the first born, whatever is the first to open the womb among the people of Israel, both of man and of beast, is mine.
Then Moses said to the people,
Remember this day in which you came out from Egypt out of the house of slavery, for by a strong hand the Lord brought you out from this place.
No leavened bread shall be eaten today in the month of a bib you are going out.
And when the Lord brings you into the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Hivites, and the Jepisites,
which he swore to your fathers to give you a-
land flowing with milk and honey, you shall keep this service in this month.
Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day there shall be a feast
to the Lord.
Unleavened bread shall be eaten for seven days.
No leavened bread shall be seen with you, and no leaven shall be seen with you in all
your territory.
You shall tell your son on that day, it is because of what the Lord did for me when I came
out of Egypt.
And it shall be to you as a sign, on your hand and as a memorial between your eyes, that
that the law of the Lord may be in your mouth.
For what-
the strong hand the Lord has brought you out of Egypt. You shall therefore keep this
statute at its appointed time from year to year. When the Lord brings you into the land
of the Canaanites as He swore to you and your fathers, and shall give it to you, you shall
set apart to the Lord all that first opens the womb. All the firstborn of your animals
that are mails shall be the Lord's. Every firstborn of a donkey, you shall redeem with
a lamb, or if you will not redeem it, you shall break its neck. Every firstborn of man
Among your sons, you shall redeem.
And when in time to come your son asks you what is this mean, you shall say to him,
by a strong hand the Lord brought us out of Egypt from the house of slavery.
For when Pharaoh stubbornly refused to let us go, the Lord killed all the first born in the land of Egypt,
both the first born of man and the first born of animals.
Therefore I sacrificed the Lord all the males that first opened the womb,
but all the first born of my sons, I redeem.
It shall be as a mark on your hand or frontlets between your eyes,
For by a strong hand the Lord brought us out of
Egypt. Indeed. So why read all that? And you may have missed something at the very beginning.
That's very key here. So what did the Lord say to Moses? What the Lord said to Moses is verse 2.
It is one sentence. Consecrate to be all the first born whatever is the first to open the womb
among the people of Israel, both of Man and of Beast is mine.
That's what God says to Moses.
Yeah, that's the command.
The rest of that, everything else while they're angry red,
is what Moses said to Israel then.
Now, if we stop and think about this for a minute, as we may not be want to do with such a passage,
we may just gloss over it.
You may notice that what Moses said to Israel is not identical
What God said to him?
Yeah, and he doesn't say so this is what God said and
Here let me tell you some things that I think you should do here's a high personal interpretation of that for when it's worth yes
Right so they're not identical
By a long shot so what do we do with this?
this. Right? Because if you start to
think, yeah, you start to push at this, right? I know there's some people from
parts and backgrounds who've been taught to read the Bible in a certain way,
who, who, you know, some of you may not know why this is a big issue, but they're
getting a little twitchy here, right? Because if God says something to Moses,
and then Moses says a whole lot more than that, by that way of reading the Bible,
It's a problem.
So...
What's those solutions now if if you are a modern old testament scholar
God help you
If you are a modern old testament scholar or a 19th century German in general
When you read this right you say aha
What God said to Moses is this one sentence and they what Moses is presented to say is this big long thing
Clearly!
This is the place where the editors who put this together from multiple sources
let something slip.
What did they let slip?
Oh, well they recorded verse 2.
Verse 2 doesn't say anything about not sacrificing the children.
Dun dun dun.
Right?
Therefore, from this we shall conclude that this is older.
It has to be older because it's shorter.
Yeah. Process that. Everything shorter is older. And this means that the Israelites were sacrificing
their children originally. And then later on, when they edited this into the Torah,
they wrote this big, long thing that Moses said to try to cover that up. I say, oh, no, no,
No, not the babies.
Right?
If you read this chapter and...
And that thought occurs to you or you hear we say it.
And you think that sounds reasonable.
Either you've paid way too much for your education or you should seek help now.
Because that doesn't make any sense.
Right.
The assumptions there are absurd.
And what's amazing is a lot of these same scholars will say that the Phoenicians never
sacrifice their infants.
Yeah.
Right, that's just like Jewish and Christian propaganda.
Yeah, I'm gonna say beautiful.
It's not.
Yeah, beautiful.
Fordiction paganism.
Yeah, other pagan's.
Reward that they absolutely did that.
And then took her out and say the Israelites
did it and covered it up.
Yeah.
Right.
So this is just this bizzaro level of suspicion.
So there's that.
If you are of a certain type of even
Angelical.
bent, then you might be tempted to say, oh, well, you know, verse two is just a summary.
I mean, that's just basically a summary of all the stuff Moses said. They didn't want to
say the whole thing twice in a row, right? So really, what Moses says is exactly what God said,
damn, they just didn't want to be redundant and put the same thing twice in Exodus. Okay.
Okay.
That may sound feasible.
There's a couple of problems with it.
Number one.
Clearly, such a person has never read the Book of Exodus.
The last third of the Book of Exodus is an exact repetition of the second third of
the Book of Exodus.
All the plans for the tabernacle and its furnishings are all laid out in detail, and then it describes
the making of them in the exact same detail.
There are redundancies and stuff like that all through the Torah.
They did not summarize something.
to prevent it from being redundant. There's not something that happens in the Torah.
That's number one. Number two, when you do that, you just made up some like Bible head canon.
Because the Bible doesn't say that God said all those things to Moses. It says he said that
one sentence to Moses. And then it says that Moses said all these things. So you're not really
believing the Bible is true at that point.
Right? You're hypothesizing some historical reality behind the Bible that you think is true,
which is exactly the problem with those liberals we were just talking about who are hypothesizing
that there was child sacrifice in the background. Right? Both of those are inventing something
behind the text that fits your worldview better than the actual text does.
Yeah.
Right?
If we look at the actual text, what do we see? We see God gives a commandment to Moses and then
Moses elaborates on that to the people. And if you look particularly at verse 13, which is where it
says, every firstborn of a donkey you shall redeem with a lamb, where if you will not redeem it,
you shall break its neck, every firstborn of man among your sons you shall redeem, right? That's
basically answering anticipated questions.
Right?
What is this donkey thing about?
Well, a donkey is an unclean animal.
So if Moses comes to the people and says,
here's what you're going to do,
you're going to sacrifice every first born male to God, right?
One or two questions that might immediately come up.
Number one, what about unclean animals?
Are we supposed to sacrifice those to God too?
I thought we weren't supposed to sacrifice unclean animals.
Like a donkey.
Right?
So the answer is, yes,
you are not to sacrifice a donkey because it's an unclean animal.
You either offer a lamb instead of the
donkey as a sacrifice or you just break the donkey's neck, meaning you kill the
donkey but you don't sacrifice it. All right. Notice killing it and sacrifice it
or not the same thing. And then the second question, very pertinent in the
late Bronze Age is do you mean we sacrifice our children? That seems like an
absurd question to us. It was not an absurd question in the late Bronze Age.
And Moses is answering that in advance.
No, you do not sacrifice your actual children.
Your actual children you offer an animal instead.
Right. And then later on in the Torah,
it's going to designate exactly what animal based on your wealth.
Right. You go and offer when you have a firstborn son.
So what are we to do with this?
has not Moses.
added to what God said. Is Israel just required to obey that one sentence that God said to Moses?
Or are they obligated to do what Moses told them to do?
Right? Is what Moses told them to do just a tradition of men?
Yeah, there you go Moses with your man made
and that's just your interpretation man. Right? Maybe I interpreted differently. Maybe that's not what God meant. Right?
And as the Torah presents it here and everywhere else, the words of Moses, the words that Moses speaks to Israel, even if those are words like about the donkey or about the children.
about the children.
That we're not spoken words that we're not spoken to him by God
Are treated the exact same way
Just as authoritative to the people hearing them
There is not a difference
There is no red letter Torah
Okay, where where the words actually spoken directly by God or in red
Well those we have to follow and then the other stuff is Moses's opinions
Not how it works, right?
The words of Moses here as he interprets and applies and directs and judges for the
people are the words of God by virtue of Moses having said them.
This is the nature of the authority that Moses has.
Because there's a necessity, not just of interpretation.
What did God mean when he said?
But of adjudication.
Right?
Meaning not just speculating, here's my theory,
here's my interpretation, but an actual ruling.
This is what that means.
Think back.
second. Think back a second. And by back I mean back from where we are in Exodus. Think
about Genesis 3. What did the serpent say to Eve? Did God really say, yeah, right? What
should Adam have done.
Should have made a ruling.
sort of exercise the authority he had.
The creation didn't do it.
But so this is the authority that's given to Moses.
And so Moses has that authority when he makes that adjudication.
That adjudication is God's ruling.
And as we're going to see, it's going to be explicit.
Some of the other passages we look at.
God says.
going to enforce it as if it were words that came directly out of the mouth of God,
even though they came out of the mouth of Moses,
when he made the ruling. Okay, this is the type of authority we're talking about.
This may be making certain people uncomfortable. I don't know, but that's what we're talking about,
and that's what we see Moses doing. A lot of these adjudications or these rulings fall into the
the category of how-to. Right?
Like how do I keep this commandment?
Right, what does that mean?
Right, God saying every first born male that opens the womb is holy to me.
Okay, well, what does that mean I should do?
Moses says, you go and you sacrifice it.
It's an unclean animal, you do this.
If it's a human, you do this.
Like, how do I keep this commandment?
It's very practical.
Right.
That's why I say, this is Moses's day-to-day life.
is exercising this kind of authority with the people.
Right?
And part of the proof of this, that Moses had this kind of authority, is that as we mentioned,
there's not a red letter Torah, both the words of God and the words of Moses here that we just read
are recorded in and as Scripture.
Yeah, this is all Torah.
On the same plane
And the Torah is referred to Christ Himself in the Gospels at different points.
We'll quote the Torah and say, God said to you this, He will also quote the Torah and say,
Moses said this.
Right?
And if you look up, I don't know, people rarely do.
If you look up the places that Christ is quoting,
it's not always God talking when he said God said,
and it's not always Moses talking when he said Moses said,
because the Torah is both God and Moses talking.
There's not a distinction. That's part of the nature of the authority that Moses has as a prophet.
Right.
And so this...
This plays out, this is what plays out, and then shapes the rest of the Hebrew Bible,
the rest of the Christian Old Testament.
So we've talked before about how what we often call the historical books, when we're talking
about the genre divisions made in the Christian Old Testament, actually the former prophets
is the more original division, but also called by scholars the Deuteronomistic history.
because the principles lay down in Deuteronomy by Mo-
Deuteronomy is a sermon by Moses interpreting and applying the commandments already given in the Torah. That's why it's called the second no-most, the second Torah.
And elaborating on them. And in some cases, reapplying things. So in Deuteronomy, they're about to enter the Promised Land. And so, when Deuteronomy, in Deuteronomy, Moses says,
Here's how you celebrate Passover. This causes a huge
huge problem again for our modern Old Testament scholars, the poor benign folks.
Wait, it says that Leviticus is supposed to celebrate Passover one way and it says
that Deuteronomy is supposed to celebrate it in a different way.
What do we do?
Leviticus is describing how you celebrate it when you're living in a camp in the desert.
And Deuteronomy describes how you celebrate it when you're living in cities because
they're about to go live in cities.
same commandments regarding Passover,
different application,
just as authoritative in both cases from Moses,
because there's a change in human situation.
But that history is called the Deuteronomistic history,
because it is taking those,
the perspective of those commandments,
and interpreting and applying those
in terms of the history of Israel.
It's interpreting the history of Israel according to those commandment.
according to what God has said about Israel.
And so, yes, there are varying views you can take of the history of Israel.
That's acknowledged within the text of Scripture.
If you've ever read 1st through 4th kingdoms or 1st and 2nd Samuel,
specifically 1st and 2nd kings or 3rd and 4th kingdoms,
again against this, as for all the other stuff this king did,
this wicked king did, is it not written in the annals of the kings of Israel,
Right, they had their propaganda mills.
Pumping out their version of history
But once the scripture is written
Right, that is a ruling that is a ruling the prophet who wrote it right that the former prophets the prophet who wrote it is making a ruling
On the history of Israel
Right an authoritative ruling this is what happened and why?
So it's not just an interpretation.
It's a very concrete applied thing.
When you get to the latter prophets, the people who we think of as the prophets, Isaiah,
Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, the 12, right? Again, the prophets are taking,
look at me, I'm going to say what God has said, both before them in the Torah,
and what God says to them as prophets with prophetic authority, and applying it and ruling on
what is going on in their time.
time. Right. Why is this happening? Why is that? Why is this army coming? Will this army
defeat us? What do we need to do if we don't want this army to defeat us? And the profits
are making these rulings. And the wisdom literature of the Old Testament is essentially
a whole bunch of case law. That's what the book of Proverbs actually is. It's a whole bunch
cases right? It's very easy back in the day.
when I did the Bible studies on the book of Proverbs, we started each one by having a game.
May have heard this if you've listened to the old potato quality recordings. Oh,
I have not. We played a game with the beginning that was Shakespeare,
Ben Franklin or Proverbs. Well, I would write a quote from Shakespeare, a quote for Ben Franklin
and a quote from Proverbs in the King James version.
So it was similar English.
Shakespeare to make it even more tricky on a whiteboard and have people try to guess which was which.
Right. And this is one of the reasons why people have trouble reading problems because it tells you
like super spiritually edifying stuff like he who makes noise early in the morning will offend his
neighbors like wow. Thank you for the enlightenment. Right. Like this. I couldn't have figured that out of my
Why not?
Right.
But how about this?
What that is, that statement, that is an adjudication, that is a ruling on what it means, part of
what it means to love your neighbor.
Yeah.
You don't make a bunch of loud noise and wake them up early in the morning.
You're considerate of them, right?
That's part of what it means to treat others as you would want them to treat you, right?
this is an application and that's what
It's really going on in Proverbs.
Proverbs is not just poor Richard Zalmanak, but more spiritual.
It's actually conveying things from God's commandments and it's really going to be applying
them in a very real way to very common, regular real life situations.
So the whole he would have the whole Old Testament.
Not just the Torah proper.
an exercise of this kind of authority, which involves more words than God actually vocalized
to the prophets who wrote it. Then them exercising a kind of prophetic authority, the same kind
as Moses, so how did it get from Moses to them? And on that cliffhanger...
We're going to take our first break on this episode of the Laura Spirits podcast.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
centuries after the Protestant Reformation,
about a radical reinterpretation of the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveyed Paul's
life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by De Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's epistles.
which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first-century Judaism,
DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly held notions
and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.enchantfaith.com
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
Young.
You have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back, everybody.
Just want to remind you all that we have sold out all the rooms at the Antioch in Village
for the Lord of Spirits Conference, which is happening over the first weekend of October
this year.
But there are still a bunch of commuter tickets available, and you can get a room somewhere
else in the area.
Ignore Father Stevens comments about camping out whatever they may be
You can go to store it up again. I said sleep in your car. Go full goblin mode. Don't bathe some of my wife's maybe
Covered the wipe off the visible parts of your body
Yeah
Stored on ancient fate.com slash events you can get your tickets and by the way we are going to have a
Tournament playing the Royal
game of Ur, which we have mentioned before on the...
this podcast. We get no kicksbacks for this. We just thought it would be fun. Everyone
who wins at least one game in the tournament will get a prize. And whoever wins all
the way to the very end will get more prizes. I can't tell you what they will be, but
there will be prizes. So it should be fun. Do you have a copy of that game, father?
Art, we have one in the parish. Oh, nice. It is a popular. There are impromptu tournaments
It's held it.
Nice.
Coffee hours.
I recently got a copy and my eight-year-old loves it.
He thinks it's the best thing ever.
Actually, all my kids are into it.
So, yeah, it's a...
It is actually a pretty fun game, in fact.
It takes minutes to learn, but a lifetime to master.
Nice.
So, yeah, it'll be big fun.
Only 32 people are going to get to play because that's going to be the bracket.
So I really think we should have chosen a hundred and forty four thousand, but that may be
beyond what we can have at the village.
If we sell a hundred and forty four thousand tickets to the Lord of Spirits conference,
I think we could all retire.
I'm pretty sure we would be doing very, very well.
Just did it for the money, huh?
That's right.
Get that name.
You know what I mean?
Run.
That's right.
That's why I got into, you know, clerical life is for the big money, the flat-
cars. Yeah, especially the Orthodox Church. That's right. That's right. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So we actually do have a caller calling in. And I don't I'm not sure that this is
particularly relevant to this particular episode, but it's it sounds intriguing. So I don't know,
let's just roll the dice and maybe you can do it in your segues and make it relevant.
but
uh
yes my segues are about as
relevant as segues. So yes, we have Cody calling from Atlanta. So Cody, welcome to
Laura Spirits podcast.
Howdy, podfathers. Thank you so much for what y'all's work. And I can make it relevant
because it says in numbers 256 that it happened in the site of Moses. So it ties into
Yeah, well, and so, um, it's the episode we're finished.
that Israel like man who brings the media and that woman.
And it all has changed to it.
It's actually, is it in the tent of meeting that they do?
And I'm wondering if that's some type of nestling cult practice that he's doing.
Well, thanks.
No, but actually yes.
Oh, okay.
I want to hear this one.
I actually just by the way,
By the way, one of the 18,000 pieces of media out there for me.
is by Antiochia Beds Bible study once a month.
And I actually just covered that passage
live like two weeks ago at our parish life conference.
Oh.
It's on the YouTube's out there.
But all I talk about is sex.
I know.
For pretty much that whole, I'm not joking.
For most of that Bible study.
It's very uncomfortable for most people.
And pornography.
So take that as you will.
There were certain passages.
when my sister was around and I was doing the Bible study of the Old Testament, there were certain
passages that Ezekiel and stuff where my sister just did not attend that evening. I can't listen.
My brother talked about this. I don't even want to hear him read it.
But yeah, so Phineas is rewarded for doing that.
Like by his line, the high priestly line.
So yeah, so this is what's going on there is these are not just like foreign women. These aren't
just big city women who came in and vamp them, right? Like this is these are cultic prostitutes
from the high place at Baal Paore. And within the larger narrative frame,
BALUM
gets hired by Baylach, who was the king of Moab, not to be confused with Baylach, played
by Clint Howard in the Corbomeite maneuver.
Oh, see, that's where I was going with this.
Yeah, okay.
I can see how you get those confused.
That's such a weird episode.
Tronya, Tang, I'm confused.
That's a bizarre episode.
The little Kato talks with the voice of like a kind of a grown man.
I don't know.
It's Clint Howard.
Yeah.
Is it pretty sure that's how Clint Howard talked is a baby?
So anyway, Baylach, not that guy Baylach, King of Moab, had hired a higher's Baylum instead of Bayor to come in curse Israel
We talked about this a little bit in our episode on prophets
It's dead. He's forced to bless Israel. But what Baylon learns from that is well as long as Israel is sort of obedient to their God
Their God will bless them
And there's nothing I could do to curse them
Bye.
But he kind of once he figures that out, being kind of an evil fellow, he slides that wisdom
over to Baylac in sort of the worst possible way, which is if you can get them to offend
against their God, their God will curse them.
You won't need to hire me.
And so Baylac could cocks this plot to get the men of Israel to go and visit the shrine
of Baal Paor.
where they make sacrifices, they participate in sex
with the temple prostitutes.
And then what is represented in that story and numbers
is sort of an escalation.
In that not only are they now leaving the Israelite camp
and going to this high place to participate in this,
sexual immorality, idolatrous worship,
giant clan type of stuff,
but this fellow who is named brings one of the
those women into the camp. And Moses and the people are there like repenting of this and
horrified by this, you know, they're having the town meeting about this for the 10 meeting.
And this guy parades past them with one of these women and goes in to have sex relations
with her in the camp. So now this defilement is being brought from the high place that
is at least outside the camp, this pagan spot, this defiled
spot that defilement is being brought into the camp. And so Phineas seized by
zeal, right, to protect that which is holy and sacred from defilement goes in and
runs both of them through with his spear while they are in flagrant a delicto
So that's why I say no.
So in the sense that this is not the Nephilim ritual, but actually yes in the sense that
this is cultic prostitution activity that's being described, not just, oh, they're sleeping
around with foreign ladies.
Right.
Yeah.
So does that answer your question, Cody?
Absolutely.
Thank you so much for your time and for your clarifications and of legate to meet me
both in October. Yeah come to the conference. It's going to be big.
to meet you father in the beginning of great land in Alabama. So, uh, I mean, both the
all in October. So excited about it. In Huntsville. All right. Birmingham, not Huntsville. Birmingham,
Birmingham. I was, yeah, I can't remember where I was. I was in Alabama. I know that. Anyway,
all right. Well, thanks for calling. So even if the village in October, I may remain elusive.
I know, just like this ask questions if you are.
All right, so this is the second half.
this episode of Lord of Spirits and we're talking about the authority of Moses. What happens
when the load gets a little heavy from Moses and he's got a need to hand, you know.
Moses is too much. It's too much. Right. So this half, this second half is supposed to
of the third half. What we're going to be talking about is two different ways.
in which that authority or elements of that authority go from Moses to someone else.
Right? Because as we mentioned way back at the beginning, you could search the dark recesses of your mind.
No, push aside the raisin brand story. I'm still on the brand and an hour ago, more so,
We said that this authority didn't just stop with Moses, right?
So this is authority.
is also going to go to other people. That's going to happen in two different ways.
And so the first one of those ways is what Father Andrew was alluding to. And so we're going to read
this somewhat famous encounter between Moses and Jethro. I consider it somewhat famous, but part
of that is because we read it a lot in the Orthodox Church, this particular passage
that Vespers services.
I won't say related to.
who? Cause that might give away stuff from our next episode.
Hit no spoilers, but no spoilers on stuff that's how many years old,
now we're not going to play that game. Okay.
Xs 18 starting with verse 13, the next day Moses sat to judge the people.
And the people stood around Moses from morning to evening.
When Moses father-in-law saw all that he was doing for the people, he said,
what is this that you are doing for the people?
Why do you sit alone and all the people stand?
around you from morning till evening. Moses said to his father-in-law, because the people come to
me to inquire of God. When they have a dispute, they come to me and I decide between one person
and another, and I make them know the statutes of God and His laws. Moses' father-in-law said to him,
what you are doing is not good. You and the people with you will certainly wear yourselves out for
the things too heavy for you. You are not able to do it alone. Now obey my voice. I will give you advice
and God be with you. You should represent...
the people before God and bring their cases to God, and you shall warn them about the statutes
and the laws, and make them know the way in which they must walk and what they must do
moreover.
Look for able men from all the people, men who fear God, who are trustworthy and hate
a bribe, and place such men over the people as chiefs, of thousands of hundreds of fifties
and of tens.
And let them judge the people at all times.
Every great matter they shall bring to you, but any small matter they shall decide them
themselves, so it will be easier for you and they will bear the burden with you. If you
do this, God will direct you. You will be able to endure and all this people also will
go to their place in peace. So Moses listened to the voice of his father-in-law and did all
that he had said. Moses chose able men out of all Israel and made them heads over the
people, chiefs of thousands of hundreds of fifties and of tens, and they judged the people
it all times. Any hard case they brought to Moses. But any small
matter they decided themselves. And Moses let his father-in-law depart and he went away to his own country.
Right. So, a couple things to notice here. What is what is the way in which this is described?
So again, I think people, even when they hear this passage, what they have in their brain is like
court cases, right? Yeah. Like Moses is Judge Wapner slash Judy slash Joe Brown slash Wow.
How?
A lot of
nostalgia just coming full throttle there. Right. I stay
over school as a kid and watch TV. I know the score. Still
kind of your deal. The bailiff. So the guy who had the real
cherry job was Doug Louellen, like he just introduced the
thing. Like Doug Louellen out there with his like very 70s
hair, just like, Hey, it's people's court. Here's Judge
up there and trust it.
Like he didn't actually do much of anything, but was, you know, considered the host of the show probably paid handsomely.
Anyway, nice work if you can get it. So that's that one Moses is doing.
Notice the people are all sort of just gathered around him. Yeah.
Because what he's mainly doing is answering questions.
Right. He's answering questions in terms of these rulings.
Right. And this is why,
I, Jethers, it's right you need to tell them how they should walk.
holocaust and Hebrew. That's where this term comes from. Right. May notice that the New Testament,
St. Paul talks about the walking and the way you walk. And awful lot uses those terms. That's because
those are the Jewish terms and they come from here. How you live? Yeah. The people how to live.
He's not just deciding, you know, like, uh, uh, small claims cases. Right. Um,
And this all has to do with the laws, the commandments of God, right?
How they're a-
applied how they work. So that's what he's doing. And Jethers is like, look, man, you can't
do this all day. Every day you've got all these other things you're doing. You're us,
but you're a father. You have a, yeah, right? You need to go and spend time with God in
the tent of meeting on and on and on, right? You need to appoint people to help you with
this. These people, these, these, Zachan, these elders who get appointed here, by the way,
in the Greek translation referred to as pressmenors.
Yeah.
Close the support.
Thank you.
It's above the pressmenors, right?
These pressmenors do not duty up Moses' authority.
You notice, right?
It's not just give the authority to them
and let them take care of this
so you can handle these other things, right?
They still have to bring all the difficult,
any significant issue still has to go to Moses.
Because Moses is still the one
who has the authority to rule on those things, right?
But among the questions that Moses is getting
asked about the applications, right, of these, of the commandments.
There's a lot of easy ones, right?
There's a lot of ones he's probably getting asked by different people every other day.
Like the same question.
And you can't just direct them to the frequently asked questions document.
Yes, does it have a fact?
Um, right.
It is a, there are difficult ones and the difficult ones,
Moses is the one who has the authority to deal with them.
and he still needs to be the one to deal with.
them. But those things where he's already ruled, those things that are kind of obvious,
but sometimes people are a little obtuse. Or maybe they're not obtuse, they're just trying
to wiggle around something, right? Yeah. Doesn't have to be Moses who tells him no, right?
It doesn't have to be Moses who reiterates it all the time. And that's why these people
are appointed. So some of the work is delegated, right? And they're the authority of the
the press.
is derived from the authority of Moses in the sense that they're representing Moses.
But it's still Moses's authority.
His authority is not taken away from him or divvied up or split with them.
Right. Yeah.
This is they they represent Moses and anytime they're not sure how to represent Moses.
Right. What would Moses say in response to this question?
They have to take that back to Moses. That's the proof of it. Right.
really Moses, they don't have the authority to sort of rule unilaterally, without the consent
of Moses who has the authority.
So the presbyters here, right, are the elders, are essentially administrative officials,
right?
Moses makes rulings on these cases and then the presbyters who are out there, who are members
of the cl-
and tribes who are out there living their own lives in these different parts of the larger
Israelite community, they then teach and administer those rulings that Moses has made in
the day-to-day life of those people.
Yeah, they know the policies that he set and they go and carry it out.
They know the rules.
They know what Moses expects.
Right.
But it's still Moses who has the authority to make decisions.
It's not like, oh now this group's gonna get together and-
quote, still Moses, who is in charge.
Okay.
Now, so that's one type.
This is Moses exercising his authority
through presbyters who he's appointed to represent him.
Right?
But this involves another person in a way exercising that authority.
away exercising that authority. But now there's
So now we get to the issue of, okay, well, Moses lived 120 years.
That's a long time, right?
As we were talking about, as we said.
But he dies eventually, and he was, that was approaching.
He knew he was going to die.
And this is where the Torah makes it clear that while that kind of authority,
granted to Moses may have begun with Moses,
it's not going to end with Moses.
It's the
Okay, now Moses has sort of rendered us this
Complete revelation of God in the Torah such that we will no longer need anyone like all the cases are covered
No one will ever need to ask a question again. Yeah, the Torah is self-applying
Everything is totally clear, right?
Prispicuous
Prispicacious
I think it's prispicacious
Let's fight no
First, thank you.
round one. So, right. So, that's not at all in view, right? And the rest of Scripture
existing testifies to that, not just the fact that there's a new testament, but there's
a rest of the Hebrew Bible, right? So, you're right, by the way. I looked at it. Perspicuous
is the thing itself, perspicacious is the person exercising that clarity.
finish him. Yes. You have to now stay there days while I wiggle you rip out my spine or whatever.
Yeah. No, and nothing happens. You just stay there and I fail to do it correctly and then you fall over.
Yeah. So that's not the case clearly. Right. And so that means someone else is going to
continue to
that same authority, in the same manner, that Moses did among the Israelites, and so there is a successor, but it's not just a successor, in the sense that just like I was the boss, I'm in charge now, I'm retiring.
Meet the new boss, right?
But this is an actual passing on of that authority.
So the authority that Moses held, right?
Is it?
also held by the ta-da-da Joshua son of none. Yes, I said Joshua son of none, not Jesus son of Navi.
How does- since you mentioned that- I've seen Avatar. Where does that- yes, where does that come from?
Where does that Jesus of Navi thing- that people's- is Brian Greek based- Greek signal?
We're Orthodox so we use the Greek Old Testament. See, look, I made the name's unrecognizable.
Yeah, yeah, how did the Greek
It's silly people. Yeah, it's silly. Especially if you're not even Greek. My favorite though is instead of using James
Suddenly, I mean it's all these wonderfully English names, and then suddenly it's Yacobos is one of the apostles Peter Yacobos at John
Yeah, like if you're gonna Yacobos you need to be saying Petros and Yuanis. Yes. Well, yes
It doesn't make sense
But yes, these are these translations we get where everybody's got an English name like it's a fesar state speeder and Paul and everything
and then you get...
you know, Elias and Alistias. Yeah. And Jesus son of Navi. You know, and it's just like you just
use the English names. It's going to be okay, everybody. It's all right. So yes, Joshua, the son of
none. Yeah, numbers. So numbers. It's a pretty joke of who's the only person in the Bible with no
parents
There you go. Bible people.
And Melchizedek obviously, number is 27 starting verse 18.
So the Lord said to Moses, take Joshua the son of none.
A man in whom is the spirit and lay your hand on him.
Make him stand before Elias are the priest and all the congregation
and you shall commission him in their sight.
You shall invest him from your authority that all the congregation
the people of Israel may obey and he shall stand before
the priest, who shall inquire for him by the judgment of the Urim before the Lord. At his
word they shall go out and at his word they shall come in, both he and all the people of
Israel with him the whole congregation. And Moses did as the Lord commanded him. He
took Joshua and made him stand before Elias or the priest in the whole congregation.
And he laid his hands on him and commissioned him as the Lord directed through Moses.
What's the deal with the Urim being mentioned there?
Well...
So as we've talked about before, the urm in the thumb, um, late of Jackson, Missouri.
No, uh, that was a joke.
Um, it's okay.
The urm in the, and the, the, I just want to be clear before somebody accuses me of
being a crypto Mormon.
Um, I've been accused of weirder things recently.
I, man, I wish I was getting a CIA paycheck for this.
Um, I think you have been accused of that.
I think where was it?
that I saw. Yes. I have been accused of that reason. Yeah. I would love to get that
money. Yeah. You're that you're CIA and also and my favorite. George. Also a Zionist.
Yes. George Soros living Koch brother. Any of you, I don't care. You any political
stripe. You want to send me money? Send please. Put me out the door. I will sell out right
Now, um, I don't care about politics that much.
I'll have a political opinion.
you want for money. I will sell out right now. Father's
yes. So that's why it just calls me to be accused of taking
money from these people when I broke. So just because you're
taking money from them doesn't mean you know how to spend it
correct. Well, that could be I've dutch though. I've dutch. Oh,
that's true. Remember, you wouldn't be spending it at all hardly.
So the urban the thumb as we mentioned were full.
or sort of the super difficult cases
where nobody could figure out what to do.
Mm, right.
You need a ruling, you can go to the priest
he can cast the urm in the thumb and through some process
that we don't entirely understand,
that would give you your answer, right?
And some people may have again,
because we think about things in a very individualistic way
in the modern world may have thought,
well, like,
Joe Bob Israelite, right,
could just, you know, be like,
Get out of the way.
know what to do and just go wandering over to the high priest and be like, Hey, man, can
you roll them bones? Tell me what I had to do. Right. That's not how it worked. Yeah. Right.
So the idea here is that Joshua is going to be the one who's dealing with those very
difficult cases. So if a case is so difficult that he can't make come to a ruling on it, he's
the one who's going to go to the high priest to do that. Yeah. That's what that's about.
Joshua is now gonna have that.
of final authority. And so, and God says, right, this language of at his going out and coming in,
remember has to do with going to war, right? And we may kind of underestimate what's going on here.
This is not just God saying like, oh, he's the military leader now. He's the commander in chief.
Right, because remember this whole business about going out and coming in, God is the one
who led them to go out and come in.
Right.
Yeah.
The whole issue with the human king is in, is in first Samuel or first kingdoms.
So this is effectively saying when Joshua makes a ruling on that, right, that that is going
to be God's ruling on that.
Yeah.
Weather got
is with them in battle or not, or not will depend on whether they're obeying Joshua's order.
So that is a very direct application again of this kind of authority. He is the one who has the
authority to rule on it and his rulings on these things, right? If he rules something as a sin,
right? That it's just like if God himself spoke from a cloud and told them it was a sin.
Right God will hold them accountable in the exact same way. That's why it says that all of Israel is to obey Joshua
What Joshua says
Okay, so Joshua is the one who's given
Given this authority, but it's not just
Joshua
Right, so that happens in near the end of the book of numbers as Moses is drawing near to the end of his life
But even closer to the end of his life in Deuteronomy
Moses talks about how this is going to be an ongoing thing in the life of Israel.
So in general, they come and they settle in the land.
Yeah.
So in general, in 18, starting with verse 15, the Lord your God will raise up for you a
prophet like me from among you, from your brothers.
It is to him you shall listen.
Just as you desire to the Lord your God at horib on the day of the assembly, when you said,
Let me not hear again the voice of the Lord.
my God or see this great fire anymore, lest I die. And the Lord said to me, they are right in
what they have spoken. I will raise up for them a prophet like you from among their brothers.
And I will put my words in his mouth. And he shall speak to them all that I command him. And whoever
will not listen to my words that he shall speak in my name, I myself will require it of him.
It's interesting. He says, I will put my words in his mouth, which as we've seen, doesn't mean
he's just gonna repeat.
stuff I said before. Yes. Yes. That the words that come out of his mouth are God's words.
Right. Because he is a prophet. Right. And you see this again and again, if you read the prophets
closely, they will have a vision. And then they will go and issue an address. And their address,
pronouncing woe upon Egypt and woe upon, right? Is that
speaking the vision. Well, how does that possibly work? Right? That's not just going
from one sentence to two big paragraphs. That's going from seeing something to
saying something. Yeah.
There are two different modes, right? And so this isn't just the profits are, you know,
voice recorders. Because
And let's stop and think for a minute.
Why would they be necessary in that case?
Meaning sure, sure, sure.
As God says here, a Deuteronomy, right?
They're at the mountain.
They're thunder, they're lightning,
they're all scared to go near it.
God says it's good you were scared to go near it
is your but
You would have gotten smoked.
Right.
It's death by holiness.
So you said Moses, that was good.
Right.
But if it was just a question, right,
of taking dictation and repeating it,
we know God can write on tablets with his finger.
You could toss them down the mountain.
You can have an angel bring it down the mountain.
Yeah.
He can have an angel just bring his messages.
If he needs an intermediary, why have a human profit?
Right? Because a human profit is gonna live among the people,
work among them, share their life,
and be able to do precisely this,
to take what God has revealed to him and apply it
and make these rulings.
Let's WIFE!
there is a human given this authority. The other view of profits just doesn't make
it, he says, why not use angels? Yeah. Why not use that? I mean, most of the profits did
not live super happy luxurious lives, right? Like, this is most of the saints have it. But
right. But you know, if we if we could have not put them through all that and just if it
It was just the message that was important.
It was just the written...
that was important. God could have delivered that plenty of other ways more efficiently.
Right, there's that whole efficiency thing again.
Right, but the other thing we see there is this promise that there's going to be a prophet
like Moses who's going to come in the future. Right, and so without entering into the debate,
because I think people know where we stand on, if this is referring to Muhammad or Joseph Smith,
That would be a negative.
Or LNG white for that matter.
What, you know, let's, let's just go.
Right.
None of them.
There is, of course, the argument like, well, is this talking about Jesus?
Or is this talking about the succession of prophets in the history of Israel?
The answer to that question is, porque no los dos.
Hmm.
The answer to that question is yes.
Right.
It does mean Jesus or the succession of prophets.
Because of course that pattern established by the succession of prophets beginning with Moses is a pattern that is fulfilled,
that is filled full by the person of Jesus Christ.
But this is also referring to the succession of prophets who are going to come in the life of people of Israel,
the people of Judah.
on down the line and we say a prophet like Moses,
like him how? Let's just pause and ask that question.
A prophet like Moses how? Well, there are a couple of things
that are used to differentiate Moses from other folks,
right, within the Torah itself. One of those is seeing God.
Hmm.
Moses spoke to God face to face.
He saw him.
And lo and behold, what do we see when we read the prophets?
Say Isaiah.
How does Isaiah's ministry begin?
You see God.
Yeah.
I lift it up at the top.
How does his Zechial's ministry begin?
He sees God on His chariot throne.
So that's one important piece.
We'll go ahead into this a little more in the third half.
And the other piece then is that like Moses, they have the authority to communicate God's
words and apply them and make these rulings in the life of the people.
And so we see up through Samuel.
There's sort of a profit for Israel.
Samuel kind of being the last one.
I say kind of because if you read Samuel closely, he lives in a whole town of profits.
So there's other profits around.
Yeah, it is real.
That's going to be a weird place though.
It is a weird place.
It's a profit.
It's a wild place if you read versus say, it's Samuel.
So I'm saying, solcums in there starts thrashing around naked on the ground.
So we talked about that a little of the prophecy episode, but yeah, yeah.
But he had there's still this singularity kind of to
Samuel and he's the last judge of Israel. I mean, he's making these rulings for the whole nation's area independently. So why does it go?
From that to they're being a whole bunch because once you get into it later
Like third and fourth kingdoms versus second kings
There will be prophets in the northern kingdom and different prophets in the southern king.
God has brought us all over the place. This is a very simple answer. Israel got big.
Yeah, just you need some more.
There would be a better way to camp at the desert to being two countries.
Yeah, it's the same reason that Jethro comes to Moses and says, look, man, you need some help.
Right. And part of what they're doing, right, is they're living among the people and interacting
with them in their daily life, right? When they come and settle in the land and become two
separat nations. There's not a way for one guy to
do that realistically. Right? And so you have multiple prophets, right? Who are who are doing this?
But they each have that authority and they've received it by the laying out of hands as we're going
to talk about more. They notice nowhere here in anything we've read. Just got to say, oh, by the way,
this is gonna stop. Right? He doesn't say like well okay.
like this is going to go on until the Hebrew Bible is complete wherever you think that is,
depending on your Old Testament canon. And then after that, there won't be any more of these.
Right? There will be no one with that authority. This is just there until we get the Hebrew Bible.
Or, per-speak, you know, yeah, by the way, there's going to be a volume too. There's going to be
a New Testament. What's that's done? Then, you know, we're done with this. And there's definitely not.
DIP!
definitely never says anywhere that oh, by the way, after that second volume of the New
Testament is written, there will still be guys called prophets, but like they'll just
be guessing stuff about the future. They'll be wrong more than half the time, but they're
basically the same thing except these guys were right all the time and doing something
completely different. That's definitely not there. Stoning not required. Sorry, charismatic.
Oh, yes, yes, the fulfillment in the case of prophecy fulfillment means it got worse.
Yeah.
Yeah, almost the only case.
In Christian theology where supposedly, you know,
everything else gets better than you covet it,
but prophecy kind of goes to see it.
When I pour out my spirit on all men,
they'll only work 50-50.
Yeah, at best.
They'll be about a coin flip.
Yeah.
So yeah, so that isn't happening.
That's happening.
But so then what happens?
How does that work?
Another slip, okay.
Are there father's team?
Yes.
All right, well, what will happen?
You must come back after these commercial breaks.
All right, we'll be back in just a second.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Perhaps you are a seeker exploring the abundance of the Orthodox faith, or maybe you're a young
mother wanting to share the fullness of Orthodoxy with your children and family, or perhaps
you are single trying to find shelter from unclean images or words, or an empty nest or wanting
to fill your time with edifying thoughts, prayers, discussions and content.
Or maybe you feel alone, just want to fight.
and solace and comfort.
Regardless of your own unique circumstances,
Ancient Faith Radio is here to help with your Orthodox journey.
Please consider partnering with us
by becoming a monthly recurring donor,
so that we can continue our mission
to spread the Orthodox faith and help support
the spiritual lives of the already faithful.
Any consistent donation, large or small,
will enable us to focus on our mission on a baby.
Simply visit www.AncientFate.com,
slash support, and start your monthly donations today.
give certain
Thank you.
We're back now with the lord of spirits, the father and your Stephen Damick and father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You know, I mean the voice of Steve keeps saying that, but I think people are really trying
kind of go easy on on my crazy brand again this evening.
because they're not hardly calling. I mean, we had Cody from Atlanta, but
man, we yeah, of all the times not to call. I know you even programmed in a little extra space
for liberalism. Maybe we can maybe we can take some calls.
Father Andrew's like, no, I have to eat at Bob Evans at 5 p.m. and then
no calls. No calls to you.
Bob Evans. Sorry.
or wave of nostalgia just rolled over me.
You know, I lived in Ohio on a couple of occasions.
So there's a lot of Bob.
I'm sorry.
At least it wasn't the poor man's Ohio.
So that's true.
That's true.
Yeah, I think I actually, one point,
I think I drove by the original Bob Evans,
which isn't that somewhere near Columbus, as I recall?
Yeah, they got a farm out there.
Yeah.
Where they like get the food supposedly.
Huh.
I think they better watch.
of locations to really be getting all their food from that farm, but I don't know for sure.
So for Bob and so allegedly allegedly, I don't know. Bob himself isn't shined,
embombed in some mausoleum. You can see him. It's just like, just like Lenin, right?
The relics of the relic of Bob Evans.
Right. And the center of a massive mega Bob Evans restaurant.
That's all true. I almost referred to as old Bob, but old Bob, of course, is the
second coolest droid in the black hole. Oh wow, man. I'm so grateful that you're making all kinds of
references that I do get this time. Max Million is the coolest one by the way, not Vincent.
Oh, yeah, of course, of course. Of course. So, um, oh, it looks like someone is calling.
It's happening. It's happening. I tell you. I mean, I kind of just put them up to it. So,
Oh, yeah, yeah, so all right, we're just gonna let this person in
who knows who this is or what they're calling for.
But I think it's Kiril from Boston.
Does that right, Kiril?
Yeah, that's right.
Hey, welcome to Lord Spears Podcast.
Thank you very much.
It's exciting, too.
Oh, I have a question.
So I thought it Stephen said that there is the seeing of God,
which is a part of being a prophet, having seen God.
a prophet having seen God and well
saints who have this holy life,
led this holy life, they have seen God.
Do they have some kind of authority like that as well?
I mean, like that, absolutely, right?
Yes. Yeah. Okay. I think, you know, it's funny when that's the short,
that's the short version. That's the short version.
But I should also say that, you know, earlier today,
when we were doing our briefing, fathers even predicted that we would get
callers who would be tracking with them.
us because actually, and this is the big reveal, this is part one of two. So there will be
another episode. You are tracking with us. But yeah, and that's that specific case that you're
mentioning is a big part of, I don't want to say the argument. I mean, it's an argument, I guess,
technically in a formal sense. But what say, see me in the new theologian has to say about authority
in the church.
is deeply related to the point you just made or the connection you just made.
As a further tease.
Yeah.
Does that make sense, Kiel?
Yeah, thank you very much.
Awesome. Thanks for calling.
Thank you.
All right.
That was easy.
One of the pressmen are just going to have handled it.
Oh, wait.
Never mind.
I say that's us, buddy.
Okay.
Let's do a
Let's talk about some foreign words as we sometimes have been want to do in the Lord
of Spirits podcast.
Words, words, words.
It's a good Shakespeare reference for all the kids out there.
What is the matter that you are reading?
Yeah, man, I have to say, Bill Gibson's Hamlet, best Hamlet.
I don't care that he's canceled.
You think so?
Yes.
Best movie, Hamlet.
I for me, I've not seen every stage Hamlet. So I can't, obviously. But I mean, for me,
it's a toss up really. There's a lot I like about Mel Gibson's version for sure.
I also, I mean, he's great as Hamlet. And frankly, Helena Bonham Carter is uncanny as Ophelia
in that production. But there's a lot I like about the Kenneth Bronock one too.
Although it is the only movie that I have seen which
included an intermission other than like you know money python and the holy grail which
is not really a real but I mean the the Kenneth Bronock's like Spartacus. Oh did that
include an intermission I never saw in the movie theater so it's been her. Yeah yeah yeah
well I never I mean that's that's long before I was watching movies in the movie theater.
But yeah Kenneth Bronock's hamlet had an actual intermission where you got up you know
could some extra popcorn. It took two VHS tapes.
Etc. Etc.
How many beta max though?
Who or laser discs?
I'm not from Central America.
I don't know.
beta max.
Laser discs.
You had to flip them over halfway through.
Did you ever have one of those?
The video discs.
That's the difference with your video disc and the laser disc.
Yes.
We had video discs.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yes.
This is what began my life of crime actually because my dad being
Dutch had invested in this, which meant he was not going to buy a VHS
player.
right for quite some time. And so they stopped when they finally just completely stopped
making them. Yeah. Uh, and that word got out. He did go and buy a VHS player and then
went and rented every video disk he could find and had us kids copy them onto VHS tapes.
Nice. Like just straight bootleg and because they noticed they had to like to record it.
like cause the video.
tape and then like flip it over in the middle, right? Right. Right. So to this day, I think
my mom still has some of the if you go to her house and watch a movie on VHS like at
old 80s movie, like halfway through the movie, this weird, multi color wavy line goes through
the stream. That's why I had a roommate, I had a roommate that had a laser display and
he must have had a good 10, 20 laser discs. And, um, and of course, if they get to the end
And you don't flip it over.
because like say you fell asleep on the couch,
it just starts over and just keeps,
and so like you wake up at three in the morning
and you're somewhere in the middle of Star Wars, you know.
Oh man, good times, good times.
Yeah, one of the more embarrassing things
that happened to Kevin Smith, there've been several.
Is that all the laser discs of blood.
You mean other than dogma?
He starts it out by saying, you know, DVD suck laser discs
or something similar, probably more pro.
way than that. But that aged like fine milk. Okay. All right. Well, we promised the kids.
Oh, do we have a topic we do? Yeah. Yeah. So why don't you throw out some people who
listen for the Ramboleger going to love this episode? And there's going to be a whole other
segment of the audience we're going to hate this episode. I know. This is this is going
actually create the big civil war that I'm looking for over the editing style.
because there's a bunch of people that hate the rambling and there's a bunch of people that love the rambling.
You know what you should do? You should do two edits. You should do like a contemporary and a traditional.
There we go. That's right. One has the guitars and the anyway.
So the authority authority. We've been using that word. Yes, respect it.
But we've been using that word.
But maybe it does not mean what we think it means.
So what are we actually talking about in terms of biblical words?
So our Hebrew word for today is smika.
That word in later Hebrew parlons is used just to refer to ordination,
like the process of laying hands, laying on hands
and or dating someone.
But originally it was related to the authority itself that was imparted by that act.
Okay.
And it comes from the root, Semic, which means something like sturdy.
I mean, something that could be leaned upon that can support weight.
So something like sturdy.
Yeah.
So is this where you get some of this, is the term snack to gay like the government should
be upon his shoulders, like something that can be leaned on, the authority is related.
completely unrelated.
Unrelated, okay.
Oh, not the word Sadekthiki.
The word Sadekthiki.
No, no, I'm not talking about the words being related.
I'm talking about the concept.
Oh, the concept, yes.
The concept, yes.
Shoulders being able to support something, yes.
Right.
Right, that's what I mean.
And for the younger men out there, sturdy is not an adjective to ever use to refer to
your girlfriend or wife.
Ever in public and private?
The abuse that happens to you if you do will be your own fault.
You'll have no one to blame but yourself.
And it won't be abuse.
It'll be justice.
Yes.
But so that's the core idea, right?
Is this kind of reliability, sturdiness, ability to support, to carry weight, right?
That kind of idea of authority.
The Greek word we're talking about in this context.
is exusia.
Exusia.
Which yeah, what so I'm going to I'm going to play I'm going to play the
etymology jingle because so many people have missed it for a
long time. I remember the last time I played it. So so here we go,
everybody. Etymology jingle.
Yeah, that little girl is now like five or six years old.
So yes, why are you trying to make me feel older?
Yes, it's on one hand on one hand I just turned 50 on the other hand.
I'm now joining a ARP discounts here.
I come to say you could join a Rp which is is you think it's an acronym,
but it actually is the sound you make when you try to get a bet get out of bed
in the morning.
I don't have enough energy for an ARP.
I mean I see where you were
going with the bit, but that's way to way to energetic and exclamation for me.
Anyway, exusia, people look at that and they see ucia and they see x and they're like,
oh, it means out of essence or something like that.
It doesn't.
It's not even related to that word to ucia.
actually from the verb XST which means it is permitted or
It's like the ability to do something,
also can mean privilege,
related to all of that sort of authority stuff,
it can mean forest or capacity,
even competency, freedom, it can mean freedom,
like the ability to do something, you know,
mastery, yeah, on and on,
delegated influence, even all these things
are used in this way in the Bible,
from that verb, X-S-D.
So that's where X-S-D comes from,
That's a form of...
that. And so that's where you get, for instance, where it says that Jesus, it says in the New
Testament that Jesus speaks with execia, that he speaks with authority, unlike the script
in the first. Yeah. And then they ask us, like, you know, by, by what execia do you do
these things and who gave you this execia, who gave you that? Yeah. Who did you receive
it? Right. Right. I mean, and this, yeah. Yeah. So that's, that's where this word comes
from and what it means actually the etymagy lines up.
with what we're talking about,
you don't have to commit the
etymological fallacy here.
Yeah, and there is this connotation
of freedom or liberty, right,
with exocea.
In that, it means you have authority,
meaning you are not under the authority of another,
right, you are the one who has authority,
and that gives you a certain freedom
to exercise that authority, right?
authority comes with the right.
indeed the necessity to use that authority. Right. So this is when we talk about various
second temple Jewish views that saw there being a second power in heaven, when we're talking
about the beginnings of the understanding of the Holy Trinity, the word power there is
exuccia. Yeah. Meaning there is some so you have.
God, right, who created everything and everyone else, right? And you have, right, all kinds
of powers and principalities, right? You have angels, right? And the powers there, by the
way, are dynamo. And it's a different word in Greek. They have power, right? They are
beings with power, but they are strictly operating under God's purview.
Right. Even the demons can only act as God permits them. Right. They cannot just decide,
well, I'm going to do this and I don't care if God lets me or not. Right. Like they could
only do what God allows. Right. Yeah. They're on a leash. Yeah. And so the idea is there
Where is this other person in the heavenly places besides God-proper?
or God the Father, or how do I know you're in,
who also operates with authority, with God's authority.
That's the idea of the second power in heaven.
And then theories as to who that is,
but that's the kind of authority.
So it's that freedom.
And so you can kind of combine both of those ideas
and by taking both of those ideas,
you get kind of a picture of how this authority was viewed.
This kind of...
reliability, sturdy disability to support the weight and make these rulings, right?
But then also the freedom to make those rulings, right?
To make a ruling, you have to have a certain amount of freedom.
If you were bound by something else, then you wouldn't be making the ruling.
Right?
If Moses had to go by, if every single time he was asked a question, if Moses had to go
and inquire directly of God, hey, how do I answer this question?
Right?
Don't have-
any authority. Yeah, you would just be looking stuff up. Right. Right. Really? But no, God gives Moses
the authority to make those rulings himself, which means he has to be free to rule in various ways
potentially in different ways in different circumstances, for example. Yeah. Different ways of
of celebrating Passover, right?
And so by the time you get into the second temple period,
that's kind of the understanding of this authority that was received by Moses,
that was passed down by Moses, even to that day.
And so they had these elaborated chains.
I'm speaking right going back to Moses, Moses to Joshua and then on down to
particular rabbis particular teacher.
who sat in Moses' seat, right, who had received this ordination in the second temple period.
Now, slight spoilers, not really for next episode, but just historically, these chains, by the way,
get wrecked by the Romans. So after the destruction of the temple and stuff, ordination, I'm not an
expert on contemporary Judaism but for a variety of reasons.
including this, the chains being broken and including where and how or nations were to be done.
There is still something that is called rabbinic or nation now, but Judaism does not see that as the
same thing. That's what happened in the past. That chain kind of authority kind of gets broken
in the direct sense, but we'll have more to say about that.
next episode. And that includes that's not just a, hey, this guy's a prophet too. Hey,
this is this generation's prophet, but there's also a concrete historical laying on of hands,
like a material thing that happened, or that was at least seen to have happened at the second
temple period, leading from Moses all the way down. We saw the start of that with Joshua in numbers,
and then it continued.
So this was not just a matter of random guy popping up every generation or two, but and
God directly giving the same authority to each of them.
This was historically mediated and handed down.
And there are communities, there's why there are communities of prophets in the Old Testament.
They know each other.
had disciples.
Right? Example, the book of Isaiah, according to the book of Isaiah, was not written by Isaiah.
It was written down by his disciples who collected his prophecies after his death. That's why
when you get all these people talking about, oh, well, there's, you know, Dutero, Isaiah,
Trino Isaiah, you know, Tertiary Isaiah, right?
There are these three different books that have all been...
been compiled in the book of Isaiah. I'm like, okay, cool, whatever. There were three collections
of Isaiah's prophecies. They were all put together into one book at some point, just like there
were five books of Psalms that were all put together into one book at some point. And bother me.
Because the sense of how how the text of these things relate to the authority of the prophet is not
the way that we think of authorship and stuff. He puts stylists to paper, right? Like that
But the style is to put...
virus, I guess. No, right. And then you can write in real trouble in the New Testament,
because then like St. Paul didn't write anything. Yeah, his co-authors are often mentioned.
Yeah. Yeah. But you also have the case of Jeremiah and Baruch has scribe, right? So there
were disciples who the prophets had. And there are also prophets who where we see this succession
but it's not just Moses and Joshua where we see it.
Most famous one is Elijah and Elijah.
Oh, yeah
Right, where again like with Moses and Joshua we have
laid out in the text of scripture this succession from one to the next right
So this success is not just a theoretical thing that they came up with in second-time Judaism
They're reading this out of the scriptures. They're seeing this happen with the prophets living in communities
having disciples
Have it right and this is the way that Prophethood was handed down by the way
This is distinct from other forms of authority in ancient Israel and Judah.
Right? If you stop and think about it for a second because how was the monarchy, the kingship, how was that handed down biological descent most of the supposed to be.
We'll leave the northern kingdom aside for a second, the assassination and everything. Right?
How was the high priesthood handed down?
in general. Yeah. Family succession, right? Your sons, right? Again, we'll leave out the
Hasbonians and the assassinations. But that was the way it was. It was not that case with profits.
It's not what Moses had sons. But neither his first born son, Gershim nor any of his other sons
succeeded him as the prophet Joshua that's right right so Isaiah had had
children, we know several of the other prophets had children, we know a bunch of
them had wives. They lived in communities of prophets and stuff. But it was not
passed on from father to first born son. Like in those other cases, it is passed
down through the laying out of hands to a successor. Yeah, there's an
ordination. Yeah. That is how this authority, this prophetic authority was handed
out. And so that being the case, right, someone might ask,
What he called in and asked it, unfortunately, but someone might ask it, anticipating a question,
well, wait a minute.
So if this guy had hands laid him by the previous prophet, what if he's a real jerk?
What if he's a bad guy?
Yeah.
What if he's wrong?
What if he's abusive?
What if he's...
Right.
Yeah.
How do we do?
Do we just, you know, hey, bad, he's got the authority
because he got the hands put on him, whatever he says.
No, no, no, no.
Right.
I mean, this is what somebody, this is what a lot of, you know, either anti-religious or,
you know, in many cases people have been burned by religion will say about religion.
Like, well, they think that just because this person is ordained or whatever, that they're
untouchable, they're unquestionable, that they're perfect, or you know, that they can do
whatever they want, all that kind of stuff.
Right this
This is what people say.
Yeah.
So there are such a thing as false prophets, right?
There are false prophets in the Bible, in the Old Testament, right?
So how does that work?
Well, we're going to go right back to Deuteronomy.
We're going to pick up at the verse where we left off when talking about the prophet like
Moses who was going to come in the future.
Yeah.
So this is Deuteronomy 18 again, now picking up with verse 20.
the profit who presumes to
speak a word in my name that I have not commanded him to speak or who speaks in the name of other
gods, that same prophet shall die. And if you say in your heart, how may we know the word that the
Lord has not spoken? When a prophet speaks in the name of the Lord, if the word does not come to pass
or come true, that is a word that the Lord has not spoken. The prophet has spoken it presumptuously.
You need not be afraid of him.
I like how it ends.
there. You need not be afraid of them. Yeah, don't worry. I mean, a better translation
that would actually be do not respect him, but we don't want to we don't want to be that
strong in our feet. That's what you're generally, you know, yeah, most of the time in the
Bible. Tell them to buzz off, right? Right. And so let's, let's take a look at how you
don't telefalse profit according to the Bible.
Right?
So things that people buy...
suggest if we weren't talking about these verses. Well, how about this? We take
what the new guy who says he's a prophet says and we compare it to what the
previous prophet said. Yeah, is he just repeating what has come before? Right? We
just we just go back to whatever scripture we have at the time depending on
where we are in history and the words of the previous prophets and see if he's
contradicting anything. Right?
That in work. What does that not work?
Well, because look at the kind of authority that Moses exercised as the prophet.
Right? Should the Israelites have heard what he said about the first born and said,
well, yeah, hold on a minute there, Moses. You're adding to what God said to you.
Yeah. That would if that was the case, then that's not authority.
That's just exegesis at best. That's being apparent. Right?
Right.
Yeah, so that isn't work for that reason.
Right, if this person really has the authority, really has that kind of authority to make these kind of rulings, then
they have the authority to go beyond what's been said before, right? Or to say something different at very minimum, something different than what's said before, based on a new or different situation.
Right, that's being addressed.
So that doesn't work.
What's being addressed here is a false claim to authority.
This is a person saying they have the prophetic authority but they actually don't.
That's the core of the problem.
And so, the way that is addressed has to do with what we've talked before about
profits giving signs when they make prophecies.
Right, these signs were there.
We've talked about them in the past, mainly in a positive sense.
Right?
So the prophet says, here's my prophecy.
Here's what I'm saying.
And to verify that this is a correct ruling, right,
that this is something you should put your faith and trust in,
that this is something that is binding on you.
Tomorrow, this is going to happen, right?
To use the actual example, right?
The Messiah has been born, the angel say.
Sheffords, this will be assigned to you. Go. You'll find a baby in this manger. Newborn baby sitting in an animal food trough.
Okay?
So there's this immediate sign that shows that the larger prophetic statement is true.
We've talked about that in a positive sense. Now you could have confidence in the larger prophecy,
but it also works the other way.
It's also a way to test that profit.
According to Drudoronomy 18, 23-
22. Yeah, I mean, if that test reply to a lot of the profits that one sees on YouTuber
or wherever these days be a lot of rocks being thrown, let me tell you. Right.
Especially these days, boy, there's some excitable people out there. Now, this may have
spawned in your head if you're tracking with us, questions about Jesus talking to people who
ask him for a sign. Next episode, we're going to talk about that. Yeah. And what's going on there.
What's going on here? That's what it means.
speaks the New York, if the word does not come to pass or come true, that doesn't mean
prophets primarily predicted the future.
Right.
It means that a sign, they give you a sign, and the sign turns out not to be true.
So, the prophet comes to you and says, no, man, it's cool that you married that woman
and her sister.
Right.
The correct response, according to your autonomy, is not to say, well, wait a minute, Leviticus
this verse dot uh
none of us is that's not allowed. That's not the correct way to address it. Sorry,
solar scriptura folks. According to the scriptura in solar scriptura, the way to address that
is that he would give you some sign. And as a sign tomorrow, a daffodil will bloom in your
yard. You wake up in the morning, no daffodil, right? You know, oh, I should not marry this
woman and her sister. And by the way, I need to stone that guy to death. Yeah. And, and,
and he shouldn't say stuff like, you know.
and behold, I give you a sign, there will be a duck somewhere in this world.
Like, it can't be something.
I like how we're coming up with the most random absurd example, right?
You know, this will be a sign.
There'll be a long pause in the rain.
Not so long is to cause you to become bored, right?
Guess not very, very baudi-pipod with this whole thing.
I think it's significant literally.
Okay.
The...
But so where do we see an example of this?
Right? Where do we see an example of this in action?
What's being talked about here in Deuteronomy?
Well, we see that in the book of Jeremiah because in the book of Jeremiah,
there is this sort of contest between Jeremiah,
who is the actual prophet of God, who actually possesses this authority.
And a whole bunch of other people who call themselves prophets of Yahweh,
of Yahweh that God of Israel, in this case, specifically the God of
because the Northern Kingdom is no more at this point.
And the jute is about to go into exile.
But they are saying different things,
different radically contradictory things,
Jeremiah, these other folks are.
So how are people to know which is the real one?
So we're only going to read part of this.
This is a long, just a bit.
Just a bit.
It's a salient portion.
This is Jeremiah 23.
You know, obviously this is the heap.
numbering, as we have talked before, hebrew, Jeremiah, and Greek, Jeremiah are
related but not identical texts. Jeremiah 23 verses 15 through 18. Therefore,
thus says the Lord of hosts concerning the prophets, behold, I will feed them
with bitter food and give them poisoned water to drink, but from the
prophets of Jerusalem, ungodliness has gone out into all the land. Thus says the
Lord of hosts.
not listen to the words of the prophets who prophesied to you, filling you with vain hopes,
they speak visions of their own minds.
Not from the mouth of the Lord.
They say, continually to those who despise the word of the Lord, it shall be well with
you, and to everyone who stubbornly follows his own heart, they say, no disaster shall
come upon you.
For who among them has stood in the counsel of the Lord, to see and to hear his word?
who is paid attention to his word and listened.
Divine Council reference everybody.
Yes.
And so here we see, and we already alluded,
as we already started to see this back in these all the way,
away back in the second half of the program,
that there are these two elements, right?
These false prophets in Jeremiah may have had somebody lay hands on them.
Yeah, right.
be able to, and I don't know if this resembles any current day situations, they may even
be able to, through various feats of ledger domain, be able to trace that back to somebody
who's incontestably a legitimate prophet, right? But what makes them not a real prophet
is that they don't have the spiritual experience, like standing in the divine counsel, being
in the God's presence.
they do not have that. That's like the soul and the laying out of hands is the body.
You don't have both. It's dead. Yeah. Right. And so without that experience, right, they are false prophets.
Notice, notice the result. Notice what God condemns them for. It's not that like, and this is the way it's sometimes presented.
It's sometimes presented that the problem was,
well, Jeremiah.
is predicting the future and saying Jerusalem is going to fall to the Babylonians, whereas
these false prophets are claiming to predict the future and saying it's not.
No, no.
And which one are we supposed to believe?
Yeah, it's what they're telling people to do or not do in this case.
Right.
Because Jeremiah is saying, because of the wickedness of the people and laying out the specific
wicked practices of the people.
destruction is going to come upon Jerusalem, unless you all repent now.
Yeah, whereas these false prophets are saying to those, as it says, to those who despise the word of the Lord,
in other words, to those who are unrepentant, everything is going to be fine.
Everything is going to.
And that is why because of them, ungodliness has gone out into all the land.
They don't think they need to repent of anything.
Yeah.
Oh, everything's going to be fine.
The pluric-
going to be fine is a problem, not because it's not going to be fine, but because the only
way it would be fine would be if they repent and they're being told not to or that they don't
need to. There's nothing to repent of. Everything's wonderful. Right. And so what Jeremiah is doing
is exercising the authority like the authority Moses was given. Right. He's looking at the
situation is days looking at the practices and this includes
all kinds of practices if you read the book of Jeremiah. This includes the business practices
of people in the market where they're cheating people and swindling people and oppressing the
poor. This includes sexual immorality. This includes, I mean across the board, right? He is looking
at those practices. He is looking at the commandments of God and the God whom he has seen and whom he
has come to know and saying, here is what God says about what you're doing.
And that ruling is
God's ruling on it. Okay. What the false prophets are doing is something very different. What the false
prophets are doing, that's why the word imagination comes up with these false prophets. They're trying to
speak something and do existence. Yeah, kind of like, I don't know, word faith,
Pentecostalism? Yes, that's a bit on the notes, but yeah, I mean that's literally
that yeah we don't you could at all that but yeah so well not totally related but somewhat
relatedly actually someone in the chat asked a very good question a very kind of application question
so the grizzled poet that's the the user name of this person the chat says so how do I speak to
my cousin about this because she believes the Holy Spirit is guiding every random vision she has
when praying, not even considering that it may be demonic suggestion.
So, yeah, I mean, what about when someone thinks that, I don't know, maybe this cousin
doesn't, wouldn't call herself a prophet, but kind of seems to think she is on some level?
Yeah.
I mean, without knowing this person, I don't know how hard to go in the paint.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, don't stop.
It's a blast to be of the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, right?
They're going that hard.
Yeah, don't tell this person, don't ston the cousin.
You could ratchet it down a few steps to...
there's a way that seems right to a man in its end to destruction.
Yeah.
But even even I mean, even in the passage from Jeremiah, right, it talks about,
you know, to those who stubbornly follow their own heart.
And you know, of course part of the question then is like, well,
where is this authority?
Supposedly that this cousin has come from right?
Well, and it's in yourself, meaning the authority is not something
outside of the person themselves. Yeah. That really is the ultimate issue. Right? Because I don't
know this person. Maybe the Holy Spirit is communicating certain things to her. Yeah. Right? I'm not
prepared from afar, not knowing anything to say that nothing that none of those experiences come from
God. Right? Like, I don't know. But I wouldn't bet money that every single one of them does either.
Yeah, probably.
And she's not just betting money.
Like that's a far more dire wager, right,
that she's making.
Yeah.
By putting her trust in her own understanding
of these things.
That's a very dangerous thing to do.
And not something that scripture ever tells you to do.
There is no versus scripture that tells you
to follow your heart.
No.
quite the opposite or lean on your own understanding or the opposite. Yeah. Literally the opposite. Figure
these things out for yourself. Right. Yeah. Like just never happens. It's not once.
So yeah, that's right. So good question. Good question. And now we conclude this episode. We're going
ask a couple of questions. Yes, clicks to think about
Speaking of people who could be wrong about things, could most sit.
Yes, you sit with baited breath.
Yes.
Yeah.
A way to get our next episode in a fortnight.
Indeed.
Uh,
Yes.
Question one.
Could Moses be wrong?
Could he be wrong?
I mean, we know he's a prophet.
I mean, he's kind of the prophet was mosaic in fallibility.
I think.
Yeah.
That's the end.
We're comparing.
Yeah.
I ask you, no, it was not definitely.
I was a links user back in the day.
But so if you asked the question, could Moses be wrong?
Well, at first we have to clarify, could he be wrong about what?
Yeah, I mean, he could definitely sin.
Yes, I mean, his wife did things wrong.
Yeah.
Right.
Striking the rock, right?
You know, he had that was wrong.
It was capable of airing morally.
Uh, he gets
certainly be wrong about like matters of science.
As far as we could tell, he, like everyone else
when he lived thought the earth was flat,
supported by pillars over water with a big dome
over the top of it.
Sorry, flat earthers, that turns out not to be correct.
So yeah, things like that.
From the certain point of view, right?
He didn't understand electricity, right?
There's, you know, he could be,
he could be wrong about all kinds of things like that.
But, but when Moses is exercising his God given authority in this way, to say,
X is a sin or X is permissible, right?
He definitely could not be wrong.
Because whether it was a sin or not,
depended on the ruling Moses made.
That's the nature of the
authority he had. And if you don't understand this, we're going to go into this a lot more
in the New Testament in the next episode. These things we're talking about here at the
end of this episode are all teasers, right? Yeah, because, I mean, just briefly though,
like there are some things that are situationally sins for one person and not for another,
like a super obvious example would be.
If a woman is married, her husband can have relations with her and that is not a sin,
but any other man cannot.
It would be a sin, even though the action is the same and the woman is the same.
Yes.
But even beyond that, if you don't understand this, you're not going to understand what St.
Paul is doing when he talks about something like eating a particular piece of meat, being
a sin for one person and not for another person.
Yeah, because it's not about a kind of...
Is that what is what's the term deontological ethics? Yes. It's it's what is what is nature of the thing right appropriate for appropriate for this person. That's not how it works at the
Scriptures. Yeah. Right. There's someone who has the authority to make that ruling.
We'll talk about that more next time. Yeah. Yeah. Another thing to think about.
Who could hold Moses accountable? Well, people attempted. Yeah.
Mary, look inside it.
His sister tried it and she became a leper.
Didn't know to.
Kora kind of tried it.
Yeah.
The sons of Kora, who made you a priest over us?
Why are they there, Bolly?
Are we not all Bolly?
Are we not all priests?
Yes.
Right.
Was there any text?
That's our obviously no, but that held Moses accountable.
Yeah.
Right? It wasn't. God gave him the authority. And so only God could hold him accountable for how he used it.
Yeah, I mean, people didn't give him the authority so the people couldn't hold him accountable.
That's right. I mean, this is part of what it means.
And give him the authority.
Yeah.
Yeah, as it is part of what it means when we're told not to judge another man's servant.
If you're not Moses's master,
you can't judge him. Right.
Is not responsible to you.
And so our final little teaser for the next episode.
That in the second temple period, this authority, the authority
declare something to be a sin and something not to be a sin.
Right. To answer these questions, to interpret and apply in this
authoritative way that we've been talking about the whole episode,
was referred to as the authority to bind and to loose.
Hmm.
Till next time listeners.
And that bombshell.
Yeah, I mean, you know, I started out by asking this question.
Why is it that this seems to be so neglected, I think, for American Christians that we don't
think too much about this. Like, oh, that's just the way how they functioned back then.
And I wanted to return to that because
Because for multiple reasons, one is a point we have made many, many, many times over
the almost five years of this podcast, which is that the Old Testament is not some kind
of expired historical document.
It's just not because that's not how the New Testament writers treat it.
It's not how the church father's treated.
It's not how the whole church or the church treats it.
It's just not that way.
But deeper than that, that kind of meta issue
that we talk about a lot is that,
and like I said, this is a two part series here,
so we've got another one coming,
but just to anticipate that a little bit,
I think it's really important.
understand that the ways that church life functions are not something that are kind of arbitrarily
decided or even, I don't know, maybe to arbitrarily is maybe not the right word, but it's not some man-made
thing. Right? That these authority structures are literally God made. God gave Moses this authority.
and God told him to pass it on. When Moses pointed ordained Joshua, he did so at the word of the Lord.
Right? It was not something that he made up. It was not man-made religion.
It's, I mean, it's rampant, of course, in American Christianity for various kinds of reasons,
maybe not so much in other parts of the world, but definitely in American Christianity.
this idea that
the way that the church functions, particularly with regards to the question of authority.
But for a lot of other areas too, like how worship works, all these things, that people
will say, oh, that's man-made.
There's this kind of, you know, true religion underneath all that, and you don't need all
that man-made stuff.
The problem is you can only say that it's man made.
really read in the Bible. Because we just went over this. We just covered it. It's
it's it's really pretty clear that this is God himself who is behind these
authority structures and functionings and so forth. It's God himself who is
ordained these things. And St. John Christ's
At one point very famously says that all I'm
I'm sure I'm paraphrasing him a little bit here, or maybe even a lot.
I don't know.
That all evils are all sin or all error or something like that stems from ignorance of the
scriptures.
And this is definitely one of those areas.
It's definitely one of those areas.
And maybe because this kind of crypto-marsiness, this idea that the Old Testament has kind of
done away with is so rampant that people don't realize they're doing
that. But if you treat the Old Testament the way the apostles did, the way the church fathers did,
then you'll see that actually this all goes way deep into that, that Moses being appointed by
God, and then Moses' authority being passed on by an act of Moses at the Word of the Lord.
with the action of the Lord, it says about Joshua,
that he had the Holy Spirit on him already,
that this is the basis for the way that the church functions.
This is the basis for the way that God himself set up
the relationship that he wants to have with humanity.
This is not man-made religion, this is God-made religion.
This is God-made religion.
And I know.
that people want to say that it is man made
because of the errors of those who are exercising
that authority, because they're fallible.
I mean, as a clergyman myself,
I know very clearly that I am fallible.
I know I am.
Yet nonetheless, it is these fallible people.
I mean, Moses was definitely not a perfect guy
and read his life.
God chose him nonetheless as this great, great prophet.
So I think in a lot of ways we want mercy for ourselves, but we want to be
merciless with others, we shouldn't do that.
And that doesn't mean that authority figures in the church are not to be held accountable.
But as we just mentioned, they are held accountable.
by God. And we'll see how that gets exercised, particularly in the next episode, because
it's not like, well, you just have to sit around and just tough it out, you know, that
there's not, you know, you absolutely ties those positions or whatever. That's not
what that means. There is a way that God has set up for church leaders to be accountable.
But most of the people who are complaining about church leaders, and they might have
good reason to complain. I'm not saying they
because once again, church leaders are sinners. Most of those people are not the ones to whom
those leaders are accountable. There are those to whom they are accountable and God himself has
set up those means. So they are also set up for our salvation. That can be tough to hear sometimes,
I think, but obedience really is a virtue. It really is.
And if we only do what our church leaders say when we agree with them, then that's not obedience.
It's not. You're actually just obeying yourself and that's not obedience when you just do whatever
you want. I mean, the way that the Bible describes a terrible and arch-exituation is that
everyone does what is right in his own eyes. It's all over the book of Judges, right?
Okay.
So yes, this is part one of two,
and we'll get much deeper into a lot of these things
and see how it works itself out
as the story gets told in part two.
Father Steven, parting shots?
So sometimes I start these final thoughts
by saying something shocking or bizarre sound
to get people's attention.
Not gonna do that tonight.
Oh, liberalism is satanic.
I don't mean liberalism like, you know, our 19th century,
German friends, liberal scholarship.
I don't mean liberalism like political lips in the United States, as annoying as Boomer
lips are, or, you know, liberal parties in various other countries.
I'm talking about classical liberalism.
I'm talking about big L liberalism.
I'm talking
about renaissance, humanism and enlightenment rationalism. Straight from the devil. And
because of that, a lot of y'all out there are wasting a lot of your time. All you out there
on the we need to save the west tour or wasting your time.
setting aside all my criticisms about whether there even is the West or you know
whether that's even a thing right. The present state of affairs in the United
States and Western European countries is not some foreign thing coming in and
destroying the greatness of the West or Western thought. It is the Danuma, it is
the flowering, the ultimate flowering of that tradition.
And we got a lot of people, good people, people I like, people I'm friends with, people
who are more famous than me and have more subscribers who spent a lot of time working
on this.
Seem to think if we could just roll back the clock, 75 years or 100 years or 200 years,
get back to that, that everything will be perfect. And your
Cicophess.
You're pushing the rock back up the hill and you're hoping this time tonight
You'll get it to just the right equilibrium point where it won't roll right back down again
Even if you manage to push it off a little it's just coming right back down
It's done because there's there's poison at the root of it
The poison at the root of it is the rejection of authority
Which is a satanic as you get
It's as diabolical as you get.
The idea that if there's a God, he doesn't give any authority over me to any other human.
That I have authority over myself and my own life.
As we said a little earlier the episode, there's a way that seems right to a man and it's
is destruction. Our destruction is the devil's whole goal.
And he's convinced us en masse millions of people that following the way that seems right
to us, doing what seems right in our own eyes, reading and deciding everything for ourselves
by our own lights is the right thing to do.
Is freedom.
Is liberty.
is precious.
Don't you dare take away my rights to do what I want?
This is just a lie.
It's a lie from hell.
The alternative is not to try to roll back the clock even further.
I'm not saying, well, what we really need to do is go back to 1000 AD in the Byzantine
Empire.
Because even if I thought that would solve the problem, it's not possible.
That's not real world.
Right? But we need to come to the realization that part of what it's going to take to get
through this life, part of what it's going to take to find salvation is finding the institution
and the people in this world to whom God has given authority, to guide us, to direct
us to correct us when our way of understanding things is wrong.
And then once we found those people, we submit ourselves to them and we obey them and not ourselves.
We follow their wisdom and not our own. We follow the way of life laid out by that institution
and not by ourselves and what seems right in our own eyes.
There is no other way to live successfully as a human in God's creation.
There is no other way.
to survive this life. There's no other way to make it to the kingdom of heaven than that.
You are not the one person out there who will just get it all right. You're not. I'm not.
You're not that person. We need to follow the people to whom God has given the authority.
and come back next time because the end thrust I'm going to come back to the...
the end thrust of what we're talking about next time.
What's really going to be important about what we're going to talk about next time?
Is it really going to be talking about how you find that institution and those people who have that authority?
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight everybody.
Thanks for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritedAncienFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook.
page. You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits. You can have basic questions
about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish in the 3D world head over to
Orthodoxintro.org. Enjoy us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. Sooner or later your legs give way you hit the ground.
They went for later, don't run away and let me down.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
and join our big old discussion group
and leave those ratings and those reviews
so other people can connect to this podcast
and share the show with a friend
who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com,
stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Sooner or later, you'll hit the deck, you'll get found out.
Save it for later, don't run away and let me down.
You let me down.
Thank you, good night, God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirit.
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to
receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory.
and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11.